DELICIOUS IN DUNGEON
《迷宮飯》
I smell something good.
有股香味
Senshi?
先西？
There he is.
他在這裡啊
I see you woke up.
你醒啦
Good morning.
早安
You made breakfast?
你在做早餐啊？
Senshi is a very fine cook.
先西先生非常擅長做料理呢
He really is.
沒錯
Senshi is amazing.
先西很厲害喔
BREAKFAST PREPARED BY SENSHI
（先西做的早餐）
So good!
好好吃！
Yaad, would you like to try some?
雅德，你要不要也吃吃看？
But I can't taste…
可是我嚐不出味道…
Here.
來
It's warm and soft.
又熱又柔軟
Your sense of taste is like a muscle.
味覺就像肌肉
If you don't use it, it weakens.
不磨練的話就會變得遲鈍
Start by savoring the texture.
就先從享受口感開始試試看吧
Right.
好的
Oh, look at you.
真是的，你看看你
Long ago, every now and then,
以前有時會像這樣
I used to sit at the table like this with my grandfather and parents.
跟祖父與雙親圍著餐桌
Always beside my grandfather stood Thistle,
而希斯路必定會站在祖父的身旁
the lunatic magician.
就是那位狂亂魔術師
My great-grandfather originally welcomed him into the castle as a jester.
我的曾祖父原本 是以弄臣的身分迎接他進城
They say my grandfather and Thistle were raised together like brothers.
據說他與祖父情同手足，一同被養大
When my grandfather ascended the throne, he encouraged Thistle to study magic.
登上王位的祖父建議他學習魔法
And Thistle began to distinguish himself.
後來他逐漸嶄露頭角
Our realm was once abundant with relics from dwarves and elves,
這片土地本來就充滿 矮人跟精靈的遺物
likely including items of black magic.
也許其中也包含黑魔法
Thistle's thirst for power consumed him and drove him toward madness.
他著迷於獲得力量，開始變得瘋狂
Ultimately, he cast a spell of immortality over the kingdom.
後來他施咒，使國家人民不會死去
I actually want to talk to him.
其實我想跟他談談
Where can I meet him?
要去哪裡才見得到他？
Talk to him?
跟他談？
Absolutely not!
絕對不可能！
Having a conversation with him is impossible.
他不是能正常溝通的對象
It was a struggle just to let my grandfather slip away unnoticed.
光是藏匿祖父，讓他啟程 我們也吃了不少苦頭
Some were even put to death on suspicion of aiding him.
也有涉嫌幫助他而被處刑的人
Simply meeting the magician is easy enough.
光是見面倒是很簡單
The magician's eyes are sensing something amiss in this village.
魔術師察覺到村子的異常變化 他的眼線聚集於此
It's only a matter of time before he arrives himself.
我想他本人遲早也會過來吧
This dungeon is like his arms and legs.
這座迷宮宛如他的手腳
You're familiar with his terrifying power, aren't you?
你們明白那股力量有多可怕吧？
But I still need to try.
但我說什麼都想試試看
I don't know if you can have a conversation with him.
雖然不確定能否進行對話
But seek the aid of the Winged Lion imprisoned in the depths of the dungeon.
但你可以向被囚禁於 最深處的翼獅求助
You should be able to subdue the magician's power.
牠能壓制魔術師的力量
This passage will lead you within the castle walls,
往前走就是城牆的內側
taking you back to the dungeon.
能回到迷宮
Please take this!
請帶走這個吧！
Thank you.
謝謝
Don't give them too much, or it will burden the carriers.
帶太多東西搬的人會很吃力 所以這些就夠了
The carriers?
搬的人？
I'll have them take you back the same way they brought you here.
當初是由幽靈帶你們來 所以回程也會請他們幫忙搬
Thank you. We owe you.
謝謝你，受你照顧了
Good luck.
祝你們好運
I know I shouldn't say this, but are they really the ones?
我知道不該這麼說 可是真的是他們嗎？
I'd like to think so.
我希望是
Yaad.
雅德
T-Thistle!
希斯路！
Who were you talking to just now?
你剛才在跟誰說話？
For the umpteenth time!
這是第幾次了？
This place…
這裡是…
Ow…
好痛…
It's a reservoir crafted by ancient dwarves.
古代矮人製的儲水庫
That insanely huge place, right? Which section of it are we now?
是那個大到不行的地方吧？ 大概在哪邊？
My compass isn't working.
指南針不管用
Dwarves do cunning stuff like that.
矮人就是會動這種狡猾的手腳
Apparently, it was also once a defensive stronghold.
這裡顯然也曾是一個防禦據點
Dwarves…
矮人…
Senshi, are you feeling teleportation sickness?
先西，你這是轉移暈？
Given dwarves' sensitive semicircular canals, it's quite common.
矮人的三半規管比較敏銳 所以實在無法避免
Do gnomes suffer from it as well?
地精也容易暈嗎？
I think they get mana sickness too.
我覺得也有魔力暈啦
Where am I?
這裡是哪裡？
Are you back to yourself?
你恢復了嗎？
W-What…
什麼…
Are you okay?
你沒事吧？
Rest there a little.
坐在那邊休息一下吧
We'll go explore the area.
我們去看看周遭
Chil.
奇爾
Can you see these marks here?
看得到上面的標記嗎？
Yeah, I see them.
有，好像寫了什麼
I need you to draw the symbols on the pillars surrounding us.
你去把周圍柱子上的標記抄給老夫看
It will aid us in estimating our approximate location.
就能知道目前大概的所在位置
How do you know about that?
你怎麼知道？
These locations typically have them.
這種地方絕對會有
They're like a code.
類似暗號的東西
Well, it means not all dwarves have a strong sense of direction.
總之呢，這代表並非所有矮人 都擁有出色的方向感
I've got it.
老夫弄懂了
It seems we're in the southeast section--
目前在此地的東南…
Everyone, listen!
各位，不得了啦！
They're back.
他們回來了
We might have found Falin!
我們可能找到法琳了！
These are Falin's tracks?
這些是法琳的足跡？
She spotted us and ran away, though.
她注意到我們就逃跑了
I'm sure it was her.
這絕對錯不了
It was her silhouette, right?
看起來就是她的身影，對吧？
I think it was a Griffin or something similar.
我倒覺得是獅鷲之類的生物
A-A Griffin?
獅鷲？
It's a monster with the upper body of a bird and the lower body of a lion.
上半身是鳥，下半身是獅子的魔物
I've never heard of Griffins being in this dungeon.
我沒聽說過這迷宮會出現獅鷲
Do you recognize the scent?
對這味道有印象嗎？
I'm not a dog, you know.
我又不是狗
It smells like a beast.
有野獸的臭味
Anyway, we have to track her down quickly.
總之我們要快點去找
No.
不要
Huh?
什麼？
No? Why?
你不要？為什麼？
Well, um…
這個嘛，因為…
It might be Falin.
搞不好是法琳耶
Well…
那個…
T-Those are mushrooms I've never seen before.
因為老夫第一次看到那種蘑菇
I want to try cooking them.
所以想料理看看
Mushrooms?
蘑菇？
I recall seeing them somewhere.
我似乎在哪裡看過
They're poisonous, so don't think of eating them.
一定有毒，絕對不能吃
I don't like Griffins.
老夫討厭獅鷲
How can you dislike a monster you've never met?
你為何不喜歡看都沒看過的魔物？
Whatever. Let's go!
怎樣都好啦，我們走！
-W-Wait! Don't! -Huh?
-等等！不要去！ -什麼？
It's risky to move about!
輕舉妄動會有危險！
Watch out!
小心上方！
I knew it.
果然如此
It's a Griffin!
是獅鷲！
So cool! I've never seen one before!
太帥了！我第一次看到耶！
A Griffin…
獅鷲…
All that fuss for nothing!
害人白激動了！
It's coming back!
又要來了！
Get back!
退後！
Sperae Yeptum Rufermus.
斯帕拉葉耶普圖姆盧非姆斯
Rufermus Sperae Alamandras Tronsum. Yovis Stantinus Histum…
盧非姆斯斯帕拉葉阿拉曼德拉斯 托羅薩姆悠維斯斯坦提努斯希斯特…
My aim!
被盯上了！
Senshi! Don't run with your back to it!
先西！不能背對牠逃跑！
-Senshi!
-先西！
This is bad.
糟糕
It happened so quickly, I couldn't do anything.
事情發生得太快了，什麼也做不了
Did Senshi have any weapons with him?
先西身上有武器嗎？
No, he was unarmed.
沒有，他手無寸鐵
We have to go after him now!
必須馬上追過去！
Will you climb up each pillar to look for him?
要爬到每根柱子上找嗎？
Well, I won't.
不過我可不幹
Which way did it go?
究竟上哪去了？
If it's taken him to a high place, there's nothing we can do.
他要是被帶到高處去的話 就束手無策了
We won't even be able to find his body.
會連屍體也找不到
Just like that?
只是一瞬間的事，怎麼會這樣？
He was unarmed…
他手無寸鐵…
We might never see him again.
我們可能再也見不到他了
Marcille, is there anything we can do?
瑪露希爾，你有什麼好方法嗎？
We'll summon Familiars to search for him.
我們可以召喚使魔來找他
Familiars?
使魔？
You're going to conjure monsters?
你要叫魔物出來嗎？
It's more accurate to say "create" than "conjure."
說“創造”比“叫出來”更貼切
There are three types of summoning.
召喚術有三種
First, you can dominate and control existing spirits or monsters.
第一種是操控既有的小精靈或魔物
But the conditions for this are complex,
但成立條件複雜
and it might attract the attention of the lord of the dungeon.
且極有可能被迷宮之主注意到
Second, you can alter animals and plants into monsters.
第二種是將動植物改造成魔物
But this isn't an option either,
這也辦不到
as it takes an immense amount of time and preparation.
因為需要大量的時間及準備
Third, you can create them from scratch.
第三種則是從零到有創造出來
This time, we'll use this method.
這次選擇此方法
It sounds the most complicated.
感覺是最難的
It is if you're creating an autonomous creature.
要創造能獨立自主的生物 當然很困難
But for now, we only need one that's mobile.
但現在只要能做出 至少能活動的就行了
I'll prepare the magic circle,
我要準備魔法陣
so gather all the meat we have and throw it into a pot.
你將我們所持有的肉都丟進鍋裡吧
Got it.
了解
Is that all we have?
只有這些？
It'd be better if we had a bit more.
如果有多一點會更好
There's nothing else.
肉沒了
We do have cheese and eggs, though.
起司或蛋倒是有
And vegetables!
還有蔬菜！
I suppose they'll help boost the calorie count.
多少也能增加點卡路里啦
Fetch them.
去拿過來
Right.
好
What kind of monster are you making?
要創造出什麼魔物呢？
Can you control it at will?
可以自由控制嗎？
Show me how to do it.
也教教我嘛
Absolutely not!
不行！
Get certified to handle dangerous magic through the proper channels first!
你得先透過正規管道 考取使用危險術的認證資格！
There's actually a process for that?
還有那種東西啊？
Hey, who's that old guy anyway?
話說回來，那個老頭是誰？
How did he join your group?
是怎麼加入你們的？
And what's with his obsession with food?
為什麼對飲食如此執著？
Huh?
啥？
Are you saying you don't know, after acting so friendly with him?
難道你們不知道嗎？ 明明擺出一副好夥伴的樣子
Well, we just never had the opportunity.
因為啊，也沒機會聊到
None of us are keen on discussing our personal lives.
而且我們彼此都不想聊各自的私生活
But…
但是呢
I'd be lying if I said I wasn't curious.
說不在乎的話是騙人的
There's a lot to question about Senshi's words and actions.
先西的言行舉止 有太多令人在意的地方了
Do you remember what he said when we first met him?
還記得我們初次見面時 他說了什麼嗎？
He claimed to have been studying monster food in this dungeon for over ten years.
他說自己在這迷宮研究魔物料理 超過了十年的歲月
But this dungeon was only discovered six years ago.
可是這座迷宮是在六年前被發現的
But…
但是…
He carries a couple of pots and knives crafted from precious metals too.
他還擁有一些高價的金屬鍋跟菜刀
And he managed to decipher ancient dwarf code.
能夠解讀古代矮人的暗號
He's afraid of a monster from a level we haven't explored yet.
害怕沒來過的樓層裡的魔物
And he persistently treats me as if I'm a kid.
甚至老是愛把我當成小孩對待
The last statement is a bit too nitpicky.
最後一點是你在找碴吧
Nope.
不
Folks who aren't familiar with our race often make this mistake.
那是不熟悉我們種族的人常有的誤會
They don't get that half-foots are their own race.
沒意識到半身人這個人種
They think we'll turn into tall-men or dwarves when we're grown.
以為我們會成長為長身人或矮人
But…
不過呢
these misconceptions are only present in certain places, like the East.
也只有東方等部分區域會這樣
If he's been on this island for a decade, he should know better.
在這座島上住了十年還不曉得 就太奇怪了
Maybe he's not from the surface at all.
難道先西並非地表的人
Once we manage to rescue Senshi,
等順利救出先西後
we should reintroduce ourselves.
再請他重新自我介紹吧
Sperae Yeptum Rufermus.
斯帕拉葉耶普圖姆盧非姆斯
Rufermus Sperae Vilal Indumreezbam.
盧非姆斯斯帕拉葉 維拉魯因杜姆雷茲巴姆
Martis Tilnunt Eesdum.
馬爾提斯提爾努特伊斯達姆
Histum Eres Anjarkant Rementalent.
希斯特耶雷斯安賈坎特雷門塔倫特
Is it ready?
結束了嗎？
It should be.
應該是
Let's open the lid.
打開蓋子看看吧
Thank goodness!
太好了！
I was worried, but it looks like it worked!
本來有點不安，看來是成功了
What's with the expression? As long as they move, it's fine!
你的表情是什麼意思？ 能動就好了啦，可以行動就好！
We can't waste limited resources on unnecessary details!
不能把有限的資源 分散到多餘的細節裝飾上！
Okay, fly!
好，飛吧！
What's wrong?
怎麼了？
Their vision is overlapping with mine, and it's making me sick.
使魔跟我的視線重疊，很不舒服
Someone, cover my eyes.
誰都好，來遮住我的眼睛
The lunatic magician controls many of these.
狂亂魔術師放出好幾隻這種玩意兒
How does he manage all the information?
到底是怎麼管理所有情報的？
I'm so curious.
令人好奇
Save that for later.
那種事之後再想吧
Right now, focus on Senshi.
首要之務是找出先西
I'll look for any foreign objects
我會透過迷宮清道夫跟小精靈的動向
by following the Dungeon Cleaners and spirits.
找出迷宮的異物
Follow me!
跟我來！
You can't follow, is that it?
你自己卻不來？
I-It's not easy to walk while flying!
我哪有辦法邊飛邊走！
I'll carry her.
我揹著她走
Izutsumi and Chil, take my stuff.
就拜託莞苞跟奇爾拿行李了
Here we go, Marcille.
要走囉，瑪露希爾
What? I'm scared!
這是怎樣？好恐怖…
Put your arms around me.
雙手抱著我
No! I'm going to fall!
不行！要掉下去了…
Stay still or you will fall!
不要動！會摔下去！
What kind of position is that?
那是什麼奇怪的姿勢？
It seems like this is the most comfortable for her.
這樣好像最能讓她感到舒適
The Dungeon Cleaners are gathering around that pillar!
迷宮清道夫都集中在那根柱子！
That's probably where…
那裡一定有…
Senshi!
先西！
I found him!
找到他了！
He's pinned high up on a pillar!
他被困在柱子的上方！
Griffins impale their prey, huh?
原來獅鷲會將獵物 固定在高處，稍後再吃啊？
We're here to rescue you, Senshi!
我們來救你了，先西！
Can you tell who I am?
知道我是誰嗎？
A fly?
蒼蠅？
He won't budge.
文絲不動
How can I get him down?
要怎麼讓他下去？
Careful, Marcille.
小心點，瑪露希爾
Griffins have incredibly sharp eyes.
獅鷲是視力相當好的魔物
By the time we spot them, they've already spotted you.
在我們發現對方之前 牠就已經注視著我們了
I can't see anything anymore.
現在我什麼都看不到了
A Griffin's body is highly functional.
獅鷲的身體機能優秀
Their wings are powerful.
擁有強而有力的翅膀
Their supple bodies are agile, with explosive power.
身體柔軟靈活，瞬間爆發力十足
Their beaks and talons are sharp as well.
還有尖銳的爪子與鳥喙
Outwitting one will be very challenging.
要瞞過牠救人可說是難上加難
Creatures are shaped the way they are out of necessity.
生物的外貌反映了 牠們必須該有的樣子
They don't have unnecessary details.
並非是什麼多餘的裝飾
Laios, what form would be effective against a Griffin?
萊歐斯，哪種外型的使魔 才能對抗獅鷲？
Do we really need that horn?
那種角真的有必要嗎？
Streamlined bodies experience less air resistance,
流線型的身體能減少空氣阻力
which should enhance agility.
這樣就能更敏捷地行動
Remember the Wyverns under the lunatic magician's control?
你還記得狂亂魔術師 使喚的雙足龍嗎？
They were as swift as arrows.
牠的速度跟弓箭一樣快
Let's try to replicate their shape.
就以那造型為目標吧
This should do for now.
這樣應該可以了
Try flying it.
讓牠飛飛看
It's flying completely differently!
動作完全不同！
We should have a chance now!
這下行得通！
While Senshi climbs down,
在先西降落到地面的期間
I'll keep the Griffin distracted!
我來引開獅鷲的注意力
Everyone else, be prepared to fight and provide backup!
其他人負責掩護我，做好戰鬥準備
Why's she doing that?
那動作是怎樣？
Maybe she needs to feel a sense of unity.
她可能需要同步使魔的動作吧
Come on, Senshi.
來，先西
Use this rope!
用這條繩子！
Good, and now…
很好，接下來…
It's fast!
好快！
I'll draw the Griffin away!
我來誘導獅鷲！
Come on, follow me!
來吧，跟著我來！
Now, back to the ground!
就這樣到地面！
It got me.
被打敗了
It's not good enough…
不行
I'm no match for it at all.
沒辦法跟牠抗衡
What should I do?
該怎麼辦？
I've got it! Leave it to me!
好！這裡就交給我！
I'll make it stronger and tougher!
我會做得更強壯且堅固！
I'll add horns, give it fangs and sharp claws!
增加這邊的角，加上尖牙與利爪！
I'll cover it with scales and even add another head!
全身包覆上鱗片，多加個頭！
With more potential, it's sure to be strong!
拓展出更多的可能性，這一定很強！
And it'll breathe fire and ice too!
噴火又噴冰！
So cool!
超級帥！
How do I take down a Griffin?
要怎麼跟獅鷲交手才能贏？
Do I need to focus on offense or defense?
我們需要的是攻擊力還是防禦力？
No!
不對！
-My Giga Double-headed Flame Ice Dragon! -We don't need claws or fangs.
-我的千兆雙頭炎冰龍！ -不需要利爪跟尖牙
It should be faster, more lithe, and more beautiful.
要更快、強韌且美麗
What's needed here is determination and ego to make a creature
現在我需要的是 強烈的自我意識與覺悟
with the single goal of rescuing Senshi!
以創造專門營救先西的生物！
At that moment, Marcille's intense passion
此時瑪露希爾激昂的心意
and her prayers
與她的祈求
brought about a miracle.
使一個奇蹟發生
I'll give you a name.
我將賦予你名字
With silver-white wings that streak across the skies…
翱翔天際的白銀之翼…
I summon the Sky Fish!
召喚天竿魚！
It's so…
真的…
lame.
有夠遜的
No, this is fine!
沒關係，這樣就好！
Now, go!
來，去吧！
-It's so fast! -The way it moves is gross!
-超快的！ -動作真噁心！
I'm going all out!
我會使出全力！
Everyone, get ready!
大家，做好準備！
Seriously, what's her deal?
說真的，那傢伙到底在搞什麼啊？
She's putting in her best effort, that's what.
她卯足全力了
I can't change course!
無法精準控制方向！
This time!
這次一定要成功！
I'll turn around and…
在轉向之後…
Punch through!
貫穿過去！
Are you okay?
沒受傷吧？
Y-Yeah.
沒有
You should take a break for a bit.
稍微休息一下比較好
We'll start cooking, so just rest over there.
我們來做料理，你先在那歇一會吧
Thank you.
謝謝你
You did well.
辛苦了
Sky Fish…
天竿魚
This is amazing.
真不得了
The vegetables are packed inside like organs.
蔬菜像內臟般塞在裡面耶
Did you still need it?
你還要用嗎？
No, but…
倒也不是啦，但是…
I was expecting you to mourn a bit, you know?
難道你都沒有一點弔唁的心情嗎？
I wanted some time for that.
還要一些時間整頓心情吧
-Are you okay, Senshi? -Marcille.
-你還好嗎？先西 -瑪露希爾
They've already fulfilled their lives.
牠們已經結束一生了
Consuming their bodies is a way to honor them.
吃掉身體也是種弔唁的方式
But still…
但是…
Fine. Do as you want.
算了，隨便你
Cut the Familiar into appropriate lengths.
將召喚獸切成適當的長度
Remove the wings at the base.
從根部切斷翅膀
Dab away excess moisture with a cloth,
用布吸乾水分
and season with salt and pepper.
撒上鹽巴跟胡椒
Fold the wings up small.
把翅膀摺成一小片
Blend flour, egg, and water thoroughly, then coat the slices in the mixture.
將麵粉、雞蛋、水適當攪拌 再把切片泡進去
And deep fry them.
接著油炸
The wings will brown quickly so a quick dip will do.
翅膀容易炸焦，稍微過油就好
Serve with sauce and…
附上醬汁後…
It's done!
完成了！
SKY FISH AND CHIPS
（天竿魚與炸魚片）
The meat and vegetables have melded together and it's delicious!
肉與蔬菜融成一體，好好吃！
Yeah, literally.
是啊，就像你說的
Summoning might actually be a superior cooking technique!
召喚術也能當成優秀的料理法吧！
If it consumes a week's worth of food for just one meal, it's hardly superior.
一餐就用掉一週的伙食 稱不上優秀吧
Damn. I should've taken their liquor along.
可惡，應該要點酒再走
Izutsumi, eat the other parts too, not just the wings.
莞苞，翅膀以外的地方也要吃
I don't want to.
不要
Senshi, have a bite too.
先西也吃一口吧
Is the Griffin bothering you?
你在想獅鷲的事嗎？
Want to drain the blood?
要不要放血？
N-No, never mind.
不，老夫沒事
I'm not hungry right now.
老夫現在沒有食慾
Hey, Senshi.
聽我說，先西
My name's Chilchuck.
我的名字是奇爾查克
I'm from a small village nestled in a basin, northeast of here.
出生於東北方小盆地的村子
For about a decade,
從十年多前
I've been doing business around different dungeons.
我開始走訪於各迷宮做生意
From picking locks to interpreting, mediating, and appraising.
開鎖、翻譯、仲介、鑑定
Also, I have a wife and daughters,
另外，我有妻女
but I haven't seen them in years for various reasons.
但因為某些理由，已經多年沒見了
What?
什麼？
-That's pretty much my backstory. -A wife and daughters?
-我的過去差不多是這樣 -妻女？
Now, tell us about yourself.
接下來能聽聽你的背景嗎？
Why are you living down here?
為什麼會在這種地方生活？
What happened?
過去經歷過什麼事情？
My name is Senshi of Izganda.
老夫是伊茲甘達的先西
I used to belong to a small mining crew.
曾經是小礦工團的一員
We were miners, but not for ore.
雖說是礦工，但不是專挖礦石
We sought relics from before the war,
老夫和其他人試圖尋找戰爭前的遺跡
dreaming of hitting the jackpot.
夢想著能在一夜間發大財
That said, the majority of our discoveries were ore,
可是找到的大多還是礦石
and finding relics like gears or lenses was a rare stroke of luck.
偶爾找到齒輪或鏡片等遺物 就算是挖到寶了
Then, one day,
而就在那天
we unearthed something huge.
老夫和同伴挖到了龐然大物
An ancient castle gleaming with gold.
那就是閃著金黃光芒的古代城堡
That's right. It was this very dungeon.
沒錯，正是這座迷宮
Subtitle translation by: Ai Matsuoka
字幕翻譯：陳盈華